Javaram Hariharan

Email: jayaramhariharan@utexas.edu Website: jayaramhariharan.com Mobile: +1-203-249-4265GitHub: github.com/elbeejay Twitter: @HariharanJay

#### Research Interests

My research leverages numerical models and remote sensing data to answer questions at the intersection of civil engineering and geology. In particular I am interested in understanding how fluvial-deltaic environments will evolve under changing external conditions.

### **EDUCATION**

# • The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

PhD in Civil Engineering

May 2019 - May 2022 (Expected)

M.S. in Civil Engineering

Aug. 2017 - May 2019

• Thesis: Quantifying the Influence of Surface Processes on Subsurface Geometry in Deltaic Environments

# • University of Maryland, College Park

College Park, MD

B.S. in Civil and Environmental Engineering

Aug. 2011 - Dec. 2014

#### Professional Experience

## • The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX

Graduate Research Assistant

Aug. 2017 - Present

- Numerical modeling of river delta evolution and growth
- Graph theoretical analysis of river delta morphology
- Surface-Subsurface relationship in river deltas

#### • Gutschick, Little & Weber P.A.

Burtonsville, MD

Civil Engineer

Jan. 2015 - Jul. 2017

- Led civil engineering site design for 2 commercial land development projects
- Provided expert testimony at Planning Board meetings and public hearings

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- [4] Xu, Z., J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, E. Steel, C. Paola, H.A. Michael (submitted), Linking the Surface and Subsurface in River Deltas - Part 2: Relating Subsurface Geometry to Groundwater Flow Behavior, Water Resources Research.
- [3] Hariharan, J., Z. Xu, H.A. Michael, C. Paola, E. Steel, P. Passalacqua (submitted), Linking the Surface and Subsurface in River Deltas - Part 1: Relating Surface and Subsurface Geometries, Water Resources Research.
- [2] Miltenberger, A.M, T. Mukerji, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, E. Nesvold (submitted), A Graph-Theoretic Monte Carlo Framework for Comparing Delta Morphology, Morphodynamics, and Stratigraphy in Numerical Models and Physical Experiments, Mathematical Geosciences.
- [1] Hariharan, J., K. Wright, and P. Passalacqua (2020), dorado: A Python package for simulating passive particle transport in shallow-water flows, Journal of Open Source Software, 5(54), 2585, https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.02585.

J. Hariharan 1 of 3

# • The University of Texas at Austin

Graduate Teaching Assistant

Austin, TX

• Substitute lecturer for undergraduate hydrology course

Fall 2019

 $\circ~$  Teaching assistant for undergraduate hydraulic engineering course

Spring 2020

• Grader for undergraduate hydraulics and hydrology courses

Fall 2018, 2019, and 2020

#### Conference Abstracts and Presentations

- [9] Tull, N., S. Rahman, P. Passalacqua, K. Wright, J. Hariharan, H. Hassenruck-Gudipati, D. Mohrig (2020),
  Determining Local Mesh Resolution for Accurate Modeling of River-Floodplain Connectivity, 2020 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract H137-003
- [8] Moodie, A. J., **J. Hariharan**, J. Caers, P. Passalacqua (2020), Constraining autogenic smaller-scale stratigraphic variability via information theoretic relationships with larger-scale observations, 2020 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP025-06
- [7] Xu, Z., J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, E. Steel, H. A. Michael (2019), Contaminant transport in deltaic aquifers: The impact of surface-to-subsurface connectivity, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP21D-2237
- [6] Steel, E., C. Paola, P. Passalacqua, H. A. Michael, J. Hariharan, Z. Xu (2019), Linking surface dynamics to the subsurface record: the effectiveness of overhead imagery in quantifying depositional architecture, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP21D-2236
- [5] **Hariharan**, J., P. Passalacqua (2019), Modeling Deltaic Evolution Amidst Anthropomorphic Development, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP23E-2261
- [4] Miltenberger, A., T. Mukerji, P. Passalacqua, J. Hariharan (2019), Comparing a Delta Numerical Model to a Flume Experiment using Monte Carlo Simulations and Graph Theory, 2019 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP31A-06
- [3] Michael, H. A., Z. Xu, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, E. Steel, and M. C. Perignon (2018), Surface to Subsurface Connectivity in River Deltas: From Depositional Processes to Preferential Groundwater Flow, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP42A-07.
- [2] Xu, Z., H. A. Michael, J. Hariharan, P. Passalacqua, C. Paola, M. C. Perignon, and E. Steel (2018), Relations between static and dynamic connectivity in a deltaic aquifer, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP43D-2744.
- [1] Hariharan, J., M.C. Perignon, P. Passalacqua, Z. Xu, H. A. Michael, C. Paola, E. Steel (2018), Quantifying Connectivity Between the Surface and Subsurface in Numerically Modeled Deltas, 2018 AGU Fall Meeting, Abstract EP43D-2746.

### ACADEMIC AND VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

#### • Academic Activities

• UT Austin: Graduate and Industry Networking (GAIN) committee member

2018

• CSDMS: Interactive Teaching Material Creation

Dec. 2020

\* Creator of EKT Lab: Alternative mesh generation for Landlab [link]

### • Volunteer Activities

• St. David's Hospital, Austin, TX: Weekly Volunteer (3 hrs/wk)

Apr. 2019 - Apr. 2020

J. Hariharan 2 of 3

### Grants and Awards

#### • Grants

• NSF Supplement: INTERN Funding Opportunity (\$44,999)

FY 2020

#### • Awards

o Earnest and Agnes Gloyna Endowed Presidential Scholarship

2019

• Walter L. and Reta Mae Moore Graduate Fellowship in Water Resources

2017

• University of Maryland President's Scholarship

2011-2014

# SHORT COURSES

### • Short Courses

• Earth Surface Processes Modeling Summer Institute [CSDMS]

2020

• Summer Institute for Earth-Surface Dynamics [NCED]

2018

### SKILLS AND LICENSES

### • Skills

- Programming/Scripting: Python, LATEX, MATLAB, Git, Unix, Unit Testing
- Engineering/Mapping: AutoCAD Civil 3D, HEC-RAS, ArcGIS/QGIS, AutoTURN
- o Other: MS Office, GIMP, Inkscape, IHS Kingdom

### • Licenses

• State of Maryland Engineer in Training (EIT)

Licence #46507

J. Hariharan 3 of 3